Bakelite Collection
Bakelite Collection
1912-2010
0.5 linear ft.
Collection contains correspondence, printed material, and technical reports related to the Bakelite Corporation.
2663962
Biographical History
Bakelite was developed in 1907-1909 by a Belgian, Dr. Leo Baekeland (who also invented Velox photographic paper, bought by Kodak); shortly thereafter Baekeland founded the General Bakelite Company (1910) to produce and distribute his invention. The material's ingredients are phenol and formaldehyde, often with a wood flour filler. Electrically nonconductive and heat-resistant, it has been used in everything from radio and telephone casings and electrical insulators to kitchenware, jewellery, and children's toys. In 1924 Baekeland, then president of the American Chemical Society, appeared on the cover of Time magazine. In 1993 the American Chemical Society named the "Bakelizer," Baekeland's original steam pressure vessel, a National Historical Chemical Landmark as "the world's first completely synthetic plastic."
The Bakelite Corporation was formed in 1922 by a merger of the General Bakelite Company, the Condensite Company, and the Redmanol Chemical Products Company founded by L.V. Redman. The patent on the Bakelite formulas expired in 1927 and numerous companies began manufacturing Bakelite items. Another company, Bakelite Limited, was formed in England in 1926 from three suppliers of phenol formaldehyde materials; in 1939 the company was acquired by the Union Carbide and Carbon Corporation.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Bakelite Collection contains correspondence, printed material, and technical reports.
Correspondence consists of a letter detailing two of the Bakelite Company's standard testing methods.
Printed material includes advertisements, books, clippings, and several issues of two company employee newsletters: The Trefoil, published monthly by "the employees of the Bakelite Division, Union Carbide and Carbon Corporation," and The Wyandotte Peace Pipe, published "by and for the personnel of the Halowax Products Division" of Bakelite.
Technical reports contains printed reports on specific products such as Vinylite.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical.
Related Material
has numerous holdings in the areas of plastics and industrial design. Please refer to for a complete listing. There are also items made of Bakelite in the artifacts holdings.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Plastics; Baekeland, L. H. (Leo Hendrik), 1863-1944.; Bakelite Company.; Union Carbide and Carbon Corporation. -- Bakelite Company.; The Bakelite jewelry book -- Corinne Davidov and Ginny Redington Dawes.; Trefoil.; Wyandotte Peace Pipe.; Bakelite -- History.; Plastics industry and trade.; Advertisements.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Newsletters.; Technical reports.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Original collection, transfer from National Plastics Center and Museum, 11/06/2008.
TIME magazine, gift of Dennis Paradise, 2013.
Advertisements, gift of Plastics Pioneers Association, 2020.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous, 1956; letter to Westinghouse describing the Bakelite Company's testing methods (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Advertisements
    - Miscellaneous, 1924-1929 (Oversize 1)
      Gift of Plastics Pioneers Association, 2020.
  - Booklets
    - The Bakelizer, 1993; 8-page booklet published by the American Chemical Society commemoratingthe designation of the original Bakelizer as a National Historic ChemicalLandmark (Box 1)
    - Information No. 2, March 1912; 44-page illustrated booklet about Bakelite published by the GeneralBakelite Company and printed by Rogers & Company (Box 1)
  - Books
    - The Bakelite jewelry book, by Corinne Davidov and Ginny Redington Dawes; photography by Steven Mark Needham, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Clippings
    - Miscellaneous, 1960; 1995 (Box 1)
      "Fifty Years of Phenolics," BakeliteReview, Nov 1960
      "Bakelite: The Material of a Thousand Uses," Antique Week, 13 Jul 1995
  - Magazines
    - Currents, 2010 (Box 1)
    - TIME, with Leo Baekeland on thecover, 22 Sep 1924 (Box 1)
      Gift of Dennis Paradise, 2013.
  - Newsletters
    - Trefoil, Bound Brook, New Jersey, by employees of Bakelite Corporation and the Halowax Products Division of Union Carbide and Carbon Corporation, 1949-1950 (Box 1)
    - Wyandotte Peace Pipe, by employees of the Halowax Products Division of Union Carbide and Carbon Corporation, 1944-1945 (Box 1)
- Technical reports
  - Vinylite, miscellaneous, 1942; 1944-1945; reports printed by Bakelite Corporation and/or Union Carbide and Chemicals Corporation, with information about various products (Box 1)
    Fabrication of Vinylite plastics byscrew extrusion (Carbide and Carbon Chemicals Corporation, 1942)
    Vinylite plastics: Screw extrusion of wire and cable compounds (Bakelite Corporation, 1944)
    Vinylite plastics: Bonding elastomericcompounds (Bakelite Corporation, 1944)
    Vinylite wire and cable compounds: Technical data (Bakelite Corporation, 1945)
    Vinylite plastics rigidsheets: Technical data and fabrication (Bakelite Corporation, 1945)